OVERVIEW

Dr. Riccardo Ferrari is a Marie Curie Alumnus and a Tenured Assistant Professor in Fault Tolerant Control in the Delft Center for Systems and Control, within the Faculty of Mechanical, Maritime, and Materials Engineering (3mE) at Delft University of Technology, The Netherlands.

His team investigates how to make dynamical systems safe and resilient against faults, malicious cyber-attacks and degradation phenomena, using model-based approaches that are robust against uncertainty. His research is applied to problems in wind energy, in the aerospace and in the automotive sectors, in particular for electric and for cooperative autonomous vehicles.

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Name Ferrari, Riccardo https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3615-5445

Birth date 21/11/1979

Nationality Italian

Web site http://www.dcsc.tudelft.nl/~riccardoferrar

EDUCATION

- 2005 09 **PhD in Information Engineering**, Final thesis on "Distributed Fault Detection and Isolation of Large-scale Nonlinear Systems: an Adaptive Approximation Approach". Supervisors: Prof. Thomas Parisini, Prof. Marios M. Polycarpou UNIV. OF TRIESTE, ITALY.
- 2000 05 BA in Classical Piano, Grade 109/110. Final thesis on "The Pianistic Touch: the Musician and the Physicist Point of View and a Computer Model"
 "G. TARTINI" CONSERVATORY OF MUSIC OF TRIESTE, ITALY.
- 1998 2004 **MSc in Electronic Engineering**, Grade 110/110 cum laude and honours. Final thesis on "The Acoustoelastic Effect in Pre-Stressed Metal Sheets: theoretical study, experimental detection and computer modelling with the Cell Method"

 UNIV. OF TRIESTE, ITALY.

CURRENT POSITION

2022 - **Tenured Assistant Professor**

DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, THE NETHERLANDS.

PREVIOUS POSITIONS

- 2017 22 Tenure Track Assistant Professor
 - DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, THE NETHERLANDS.
- 2015 17 **Postdoctoral Researcher**

DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, THE NETHERLANDS.

2013 - 15 **R&D Executive Manager**

DANIELI AUTOMATION, ITALY.

2008 - 13 **Junior R&D Engineer**

DANIELI AUTOMATION, ITALY.

FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

2021 **Best Paper Award**, Finalist

ASME ENERGY SYSTEMS TECHNICAL COMMITTEE, ACC 2021.

- 2020 **Aerospace Industrial Benchmark on Fault Detection**, First Prize AIRBUS, IFAC WORLD CONGRESS 2020.
- 2018 **Paul M. Frank Award**, Honourable mention IFAC, SAFEPROCESS 2018.
- 2016 18 **Marie Skłowdowska-Curie Individual Fellowship**, SURE: Safe Unmanned Robotic Ensembles EUROPEAN COMMISSION, GRANT NO. 707546.
 - 2011 Competition on Fault Detection and Fault Tolerant Control for Wind Turbines, Second place THE MATHWORKS AND K.K. ELECTRONICS, IFAC WORLD CONGRESS 2011.

2005 **Giacomini Award**, Awarded to best Italian MSc thesis in Acoustics ITALIAN ACOUSTICS ASSOCIATION.

SUPERVISION OF GRADUATE STUDENTS AND POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWS

DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS

- 2021 (25) Mahmood Mirzakhalili (PhD).
- 2021 (25) **Tushar Desai (PhD)**.
- 2021 (24) **Alex Gallo (Postdoc)**.
- 2020 (24) **Jean Gonzales Silva (PhD)**.
- 2020 (24) **Zhixin Feng (PhD)**.
- 2020 (24) Atindriyo Kusumo Pamososuryo (PhD).
 - 2020 21 **Joeri Frederik (PhD, graduated)**, Co-supervisor.
- 2018 21 Yichao Liu (Postdoc).
- 2018 (22) **Twan Keijzer (PhD)**.
 - 2018 Niloofar Jahanshahi (PhD).

DANIELI AUTOMATION AND UNIV. OF TRIESTE, ITALY

2010 - 13 Francesca Boem (PhD, graduated), Co-supervisor.

SUPERVISION OF UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS

- 2021 **11 MSc students**, Supervisor for their final MSc projects

 DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS.
- 2015 21 **30 MSc students, 12 BSc students**, Supervisor for their final MSc and BSc projects, respectively DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS.
- 2008 15 **6 MSc students**, Supervisor for their final MSc DANIELI AUTOMATION AND UNIV. OF TRIESTE, ITALY.

TEACHING ACTIVITIES

- Organizer and Lecturer (PhD), "DISC Summer PhD School: Security and Resiliency for Cyber-Physical Systems foundations and recent advances"

 DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS.
- 2018 **Lecturer** (**MSc**), "Fault Diagnosis and Fault Tolerant Control", obligatory specialization course DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS. about 60 students
- 2016 **Lecturer (MSc)**, "Control Systems Laboratory", obligatory specialization course DELFT CENTER FOR SYSTEMS AND CONTROL/3ME/TU DELFT, NETHERLANDS. about 70 students

ORGANIZATION OF SCIENTIFIC MEETINGS

- 2022 **SafeProcess**, Proposer of pre-conference workshop on Security of Cyber-Physical Systems **IFAC**, PAFOS (CYPRUS), JUNE 7-10 2022.
- European Control Conference, Organization of Invited Session on Security and Resiliency for Cyber-Physical Systems
 IEEE, IFAC, ROTTERDAM (THE NETHERLANDS), JUNE 29-JULY 2 2020.
- 2019 **15th IFAC Symposium on Large Scale Complex Systems**, National Organizing Committee IFAC, DELFT, MAY 26-28 2019.
- 2018 **SafeProcess**, Organization of Invited Session on Safety and Privacy of Cyber Physical Systems IFAC, WARSAW, AUGUST 29-31 2018.

2018 **European Control Conference**, Organization of Invited Session on Safety, Security and Privacy of Cyber Physical Systems

IEEE, IFAC, LIMASSOL (CYPRUS), AUGUST 29-31 2018.

EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES

- 2021 **Moderator**, Electrical Engineering and Systems Science Mathematics ARXIV.
- 2018 **Associate Editor**, Conference Editorial Board IEEE CONTROL SYSTEMS SOCIETY (CSS).
- 2015 **Associate Editor**, Conference Editorial Board EUROPEAN CONTROL ASSOCIATION (EUCA).
- 2005 Reviewer, IEEE Trans. on Automatic Control, Automatica, Int. J. of Control, IEEE Trans. on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, IEEE Trans. on Signal Processing; Conf. on Decision and Control, American Control Conf., European Control Conf.
 IEEE AND IFAC.

MEMBERSHIP OF SCIENTIFIC SOCIETIES

- 2015 Member, Technical Committee 6.4 on Fault Detection, Supervision & Safety of Technical Processes
 IFAC.
- 2005 **Member**, Control Systems Society IEEE.

RESEARCH VISITS AND INVITED TALKS

- 2021 **Sparse model identification**, with Kausihan Selvam AB VOLVO, SWEDEN.
- The dual role of uncertainty, with Prof. Henrik Sandberg KTH STOCKHOLM, SWEDEN.
- 2021 **Safety and Security**, with Prof. K.G. Robbersmyr UNIV. OF AGDER, NORWAY.
- 2019 **Anomaly detection for cooperative vehicles**, with Prof. J.M. Maestre UNIV. OF SEVILLE, SPAIN.
- 2019 **Sliding mode anomaly detection**, with Fabian Jarmolowitz BOSCH RESEARCH, GERMANY.
- 2018 **Distributed Fault Diagnosis**, with Prof. Claudio de Persis UNIV. OF GRONINGEN, NETHERLANDS.
- 2017 **Distributed Cyber-attack Detection**, with Prof. Michel Kinnaert UNIV. LIBRE DE BRUXELLES, BELGIUM.
- 2017 Distributed Fault Diagnosis and Cyber-attack Detection in Large–Scale Systems, with Prof. Ali Karimoddini NORTH CAROLINA A&T STATE UNIVERSITY, USA.
- 2017 **Graduate school seminar on fault diagnosis**, with Dr. Daniele Casagrande UNIV. OF UDINE (IT), ITALY.
- 2016 **Fault diagnosis of smart buildings**, with Ondrej Holub HONEYWELL LABS PRAGUE, CZECH REPUBLIC.
- 2013 **Distributed Fault Diagnosis**, with Alexandru Caracas IBM RESEARCH ZURICH, SWITZERLAND.
- Algebraic methods, with Prof. T. Parisini IMPERIAL COLLEGE LONDON, UK.

INSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES

- 2021 **Member**, Faculty-wide Commission on Frauds

 Delft Center for Systems and Control/3ME/TU Delft, The Netherlands.
- 2020 **Member**, Board of Examiners

 Delft Center for Systems and Control/3ME/TU Delft, The Netherlands.
- 2019 **Expert**, serving as reviewer for MSCA grant applications EUROPEAN COMMISSION, BRUXELLES, BELGIUM.
- 2018 19 **Expert**, serving as reviewer for grant applications VLAANDEREN AGENTSCHAP INNOVEREN & ONDERNEMEN, BRUXELLES, BELGIUM.

TRAINING AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT

- 2020 **Personal Development Program**, Career development course for Tenure Trackers Delft Center for Systems and Control/3ME/TU Delft, The Netherlands.
- 2017 19 University Teaching Qualification

 Delft Center for Systems and Control/3ME/TU Delft, The Netherlands.

Appendix 1: Previous and ongoing funding

As a TU Delft researcher, I contributed to secure a total of 1.9 M \in of public and private funding for my Department, of which 1.5 M \in in currently active projects.

Previous grants

Title	Funding Source	Amount (own)	Period	Role	Project Goal
D3P	3mE, Cohesion grant	60 k€	10/2018 - 9/2019	Co-PI	Investigation of diagnosis and prognosis of structural damages in offshore structures.
SURE	EU, MSCA	177 k€	9/2016 - 9/2018	PI	Deriving distributed fault diagnosis methods for cooperative autonomous robotic vehicles.
EDOWE	EU, MSCA	176 k€	10/2019 - 9/2021	Host	Application of advanced control methods to offshore wind turbines to decrease their cost of energy. Grantee: Dr. Yichao Liu.

On-going Grants

Title	Funding Source	Amount (own)	Period	Role	Project Goal
SPARSITY	Volvo AB	600 k€	1/2021 - 12/2024	PI	Using sparse data for implementing predictive maintenance of electric heavy vehicles.
AIMWIND	Research Council of Norway	1.55 M€ (328 k€)	1/2021 - 12/2023	Co-PI	Optimization of the longevity and profitability of offshore wind farms via health-aware control.
WATEREYE	EU, H2020	4.7 M€ (590 k€)	11/2019 - 10/2022	Co-PI	Deriving fault tolerant control laws for offshore wind farms subjected to corrosion degradation.

Appendix 2: Publication output

A. Bibliometrics and summary of publication activities

I have (co-)authored so far **62 scientific peer-reviewed publications, of which 27 in the years 2020-22**. They have been featured in 8 flagship journals and 10 conference series in the disciplines of Automatic Control, Robotics and Renewable Energies. I have (co-)authored 16 scientific journal articles and 46 conference papers. I am the first editor of a book published by Springer Nature, and wrote 4 book chapters.

According to Google Scholar (GS) my works have been cited 1107 times and my h-index is 16 at the time of writing. Bibliometrics data provided by Scopus (SC), instead, amounts to 801 citations (698 excluding my self citations, 562 excluding self citations from all authors) and my h-index is 13.